Good morning class. Welcome to our first class.
早上好，大家！欢迎来到我们的第一节课。
And today,
今天，我想做的是提供……
what I want to do is provide the
framework for how we will learn this semester.
本学期学习的框架。
What are we learning? How are we learning?
我们在学什么？我们怎么学？
Why are we learning? Alright, so
我们为什么学？好了，开始吧。
this is a class of ideas.
这是一堂关于思想的课。
So it's really important for you to pay attention
所以你们认真听讲非常重要。
and understand how these ideas connect with each other.
并且要理解这些思想彼此之间的联系。
If I'm not being clear, ask me a question.
如果我说得不清楚，问我一个问题。
In fact, make it a habit to ask as many questions as possible
实际上，养成尽可能多问问题的习惯。
because that way you will learn more,
因为这样你会学得更多。
learning will be more fun for you, and learning will be much more clearer to you, okay?
学习会更有趣，学习也会更清晰，好的？
So let's get in the habit of asking questions.
让我们养成提问的习惯吧。
So wherever I am confusing,
只要我说得不清楚，随时打断。
wherever I'm speaking too fast, wherever you don't understand,
无论我说得多快，还是你不懂，随时打断。
interrupt me, okay?
让我们养成提问的习惯。
Let's get in the habit. Alright, so
好了，开始吧。
I first want to
我先想说说
talk about Immanuel Kant.
伊曼努尔·康德。
We will be discussing him a lot this semester because
本学期我们会多谈他。
he is the greatest philosopher in Western history.
他是西方史上最伟大的哲学家。
And he teaches us,
他教给我们，
he taught us how the world works.
他教我们世界是怎样运作的。
And this is what he told us.
这就是他告诉我们的内容。
He told us that
他告诉我们，
we can
我们可以
never know the objective reality.
从未曾知晓客观实相。
There is an objective reality,
有客观实相，
what he calls the nomina,
他所称之名词。
okay?
好的？
Or the things in...
或者是那里的事物……
themselves. That
本身。
is not knowable to us.
它不为我们所知。
That is a world we can never access.
那是我们永远无法触及的世界。
Why? Because
为什么？因为…
we perceive the world through our senses.
我们通过感官感知世界。
Our senses, our perception warps the world
我们的感官与感知扭曲世界，
and changes it into a structure
并将其变为结构。
that we can process called the phenomena.
我们可以处理的那部分叫做现象。
And we build
然后我们构建……
Ub Ub
Ub
Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub
Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub
Ub
Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub understand reality we need to add in time
and space and that's the example all right
和空间，这就是例子，好的。
so how the world works is we perceive the world we perceive the nomina and
所以世界运作的方式是我们感知世界，我们感知名词并且……
turn it into the phenomena for us to process in other words and
把它转化为现象，以便我们处理，换句话说……
this is really important reality is what we imagine it
这件事真的很重要，现实就是我们想象的那样
to be there is no objective
在那里没有客观的存在
reality reality is what we imagine it to be
现实就是我们想象的那样
life is a constant process a constant act of imagination
生命是一场不断的过程，一场不断的想象行为
all right that's that's Emmanuel Kant that's the
好的，就是这样，埃马纽埃尔·康德的意思是
first idea i want you to understand
第一点，我想让你理解
so
好
what i want i want to do in this class this semester is train you or
我想在这学期的这门课里做的事是训练你，或者说教你，或者激发你去扩展你的想象力。
teach you or inspire you to augment your imagination
so that
于是这样
you see the world much more clearly
你会更清晰地看到世界
this class is not about what to think it's about how to think
这门课不是讲什么想法，而是讲怎么想法
all right all right so
好的，好的，好的。
let me explain the structure of the course
让我来解释一下这门课的结构。
so there's past there's present
先是过去，再是现在。
and there's future
还有未来
we'll be looking at all three this semester the past the present
我们将在本学期把过去、现在和未来都放进去
and the future we were analyzing all three
我们正在分析这三者
in order to construct a more
为构建更客观的现实
objective reality for ourselves we will
我们将会成功
not succeed we will fail but
我们会失败
the process is going to be a real process we will not succeed we will fail but
过程将是真正的过程，我们会成功，我们会失败，但…
the process of trying will train our minds to think much more critically about the world
尝试的过程将训练我们的思维，使我们更批判性地思考世界
so let me explain how in the
所以让我来解释如何在…
present we have geopolitics we'll be studying geopolitics
现在我们有地缘政治，我们将学习地缘政治
for example why is there war in Ukraine why
例如，为什么乌克兰会有战争，为什么…
is there war in the middle east what will happen we'll be studying geopolitics
为什么中东会有战争，接下来会怎样，我们将学习地缘政治
and we'll try to understand why this is happening
我们会尝试理解这件事发生的原因
we'll try to formulate an analytical model of geopolitics.
我们会尝试构建一个地缘政治的分析模型
Okay? An analytical model.
好的？一个分析模型。
We will then
我们随后会
use this analytical model to make predictions about the future.
用这个分析模型来预测未来。
Why do we do this? Because
我们这么做的原因是
these predictions will tell us if
这些预测会告诉我们
our analytical model is correct or not.
我们的分析模型是否正确。
Okay? Does that make sense?
好的？这样说通吗？
It's no different from artificial intelligence.
它与人工智能没有区别。
How do you know if your artificial intelligence, the model is correct or not?
你怎么知道你的人工智能模型是否正确？
When you test it against reality.
当你把它与现实对照时。
Okay? There's no difference between that
好的？那两者之间没有区别。
artificial intelligence system and what we're trying to do here.
人工智能系统和我们在这里尝试的东西没有区别。
And why are we doing this?
我们为什么要这么做呢？
Because if we're able to have an actual model
因为如果我们能有一个真正能做出正确预测的模型，那就可以把这一切都拿回去分析过去。
that makes correct predictions, then
我们可以把这一切都拿回去分析过去。
we can take all this and go back and analyze the past.
To reveal the secret
揭示世界的秘密
history of the world.
历史
That is a project we are undertaking this semester.
这是一项我们本学期正在进行的项目
To discover for ourselves the secret history of humanity.
为我们自己发现人类的秘密历史。
Because you may not know this,
因为你可能不知道这一点，
but all the history that you learn in school, all
但你在学校学到的所有历史，全部
that history that you think you know, it is
你以为自己知道的那段历史，实际上是
false. Okay?
是假的。好吗？
The history that you know, the history
你所知的那段历史，那个历史
that you believe,
你所相信的那段历史，
is a system implanted into
是由强大的人们植入你们大脑中的系统。
your brains by powerful people.
Okay? So the real question that we're looking at this semester is really,
好的？所以本学期我们真正要探讨的核心问题是，
how does
那么，
power work?
权力是如何运作的？
work. Because
工作。因为
if we can figure this out, then you will achieve liberation,
如果我们能搞清楚这点，随后你就能获得解放，
you achieve freedom, you understand how you're being manipulated by others.
你获得自由，你就会明白别人是怎样操控你的。
And therefore, you'll be free,
于是你就自由了，
you'll be empowered to live the way you want to live,
你将有能力按自己的方式生活，
to see the world that is true to you. So
去见证真正属于你的世界。
let me give you three career examples of how power works.
让我给你举三个职业例子来说明权力是怎么运作的。
Okay, the first example is money.
好的，第一个例子是钱。
Let us do a thought experiment.
让我们做一个思考实验。
I'm a bank, okay, I decide I want to open a bank.
我是一家银行，好的，我决定开一家银行。
And now you're allowed to put money in the bank.
现在你们可以把钱存进银行。
Okay, so all of you get together and
好了，大家一起把钱放进去。
you put $5 million in the bank.
你把500万存进银行。
Not $5 million. Now, why do you put $5 million into my bank?
不是500万。现在，为什么你把500万存进我的银行？
Because I promise you 1% interest.
因为我答应你1%的利息。
Right? 1% interest.
对吧？1%利息。
That's a really good deal. But now because
这真是个好交易。可现在因为……
I owe you some money, right, I owe you 1% interest,
我欠你钱，对吧，我欠你1%利息。
I now need to go make money for myself.
我现在需要去为自己赚钱。
So I have a friend who's building a restaurant
于是我有个朋友正在建一家餐厅。
and he says, I need $5 million to build a restaurant.
他说：我需要500万来建餐厅。
And after a year, I will pay back 10% interest.
一年后，我会付10%的利息。
Okay? 10% interest. And so
好的？10%的利息。于是……
I make a 9% profit and I can use that to pay my employees,
我赚了9%的利润，可以用来支付员工。
to pay myself a salary, to build a new building.
给自己发工资，建一座新楼。
Okay? So now I want you to think about this.
好？现在请你们想想这个。
I'm a bank, I got $5 million in deposit money,
我是银行，我存了500万。
then I gave out a $5 million loan.
然后我发了5百万的贷款。
Today, how much money do I have?
今天，我手里有多少钱？
How much money is in the bank? Countless.
银行里有多少钱？无数。
Hmm? Countless.
嗯？无数。
How much money now do I have?
现在我手里有多少钱？
I got $5 million from you guys, then I gave it out to someone else.
我从你们那里拿了500万，然后又发给别人。
Right? So how much money is in the bank right now?
对吧？现在银行里有多少钱？
Zero. Zero, right?
零。零，对吧？
It should be zero.
应该是零。
Logically, the answer is zero.
逻辑上答案是零。
In fact, zero is the answer that you are taught in economics.
实际上零就是你们在经济学里学到的答案。
It's what you are taught.
这就是你们学到的答案。
Yeah? Zero is not an answer that we're taught in economics.
是吗？零不是我们在经济学里学到的答案。
Okay. You cannot loan all the money that you have.
好的。你不能把所有的钱都贷出去。
Like, for example, they will have a limit,
比如说，他们会有一个额度限制。
like 25%,
像25%，
I don't know, maybe 10%, so you can only loan like $4 million.
我不知道，可能10%，所以你只能贷大约400万美元。
Okay, okay, yeah. Okay. Really good point.
好的，好的，嗯。真的很好的点。
Okay. Oh, yes. Okay. So that's really good.
好的。哦，是的。好的。所以这真的很好。
So in economics, you learn about the idea of the five -year balance.
在经济学里，你会学到五年平衡的概念。
Okay. And you learn about the idea of the fractional reserve system.
好的。你还会学到分数准备金制度的概念。
Okay? What's fractional reserve?
好的？什么是分数准备金？
As you say, you must leave behind a certain amount of money.
正如你所说，你必须留存一定金额的现金。
It could be 7%, it could be 10%, it depends on the country.
可以是7%，也可以是10%，取决于各国。
Okay? Let's say 10%. So theoretically, I cannot actually lend out $5 million.
好的？设定10%。理论上，我就不能真正借出500万。
I'm going to lend out $4.5 million.
我准备借出450万。
Okay? You're right.
好的？你说得对。
Okay? That's law as well.
好的？这也是法律。
Okay? So,
好的？那么，
actually, okay,
实际上，好的，
let's say I lend out $4.5 million.
设定我借出450万。
Okay? Now how much money do I have in the bank?
好的？现在我在银行里有多少钱？
$2.5 million.
250万。
Yeah, half a million. Right?
是的，五十万。对吗？
Okay. So again, this is what you're taught in economics.
好的。那么，再说一次，这就是你在经济学里学到的内容。
This is what makes logical sense.
这就是逻辑上成立的结果。
Right? The correct answer,
对吗？正确答案是，
what actually happens in real life,
实际生活中发生的事是，
is you now have $9.5 million.
你现在手里有950万。
Okay. That is the correct answer.
好的。那是正确答案。
This makes no sense.
这没有道理。
Right? But it happens in reality.
对吗？但它在现实中发生。
And how do we know? Because over the past 20 years,
而我们怎么知道呢？因为过去20年里，
Chinese banks, like the Bank of China,
中国银行，如中国银行，
the Bank of Industry and Commerce, the Agriculture Bank of China,
中国工商银行、农业银行
if you Google these banks,
如果你在谷歌搜索这些银行，
what you will see is these past 20 years,
你会看到过去20年的情况，
these banks have become the largest in the world.
这些银行已成为世界上最大的。
How did that happen? Was it
那是怎么回事？是……
because Chinese people got rich and put all the money in the bank?
是因为中国人变得富裕，把钱都存进银行吗？
No, that's not what happened.
不是，事情不是那样发生的。
What happened, guys? Supported by the government. Okay.
发生了什么？得到政府支持。好了。
What happened was these banks start to lend money out to corporations,
这些银行开始向企业、政府和个人放贷。
to government, to people,
to build skyscrapers, to build roads.
建高楼、修道路。
In other words,
换句话说，
the banks started to create money out
银行开始创造货币。
of nothing in order to finance China's infrastructure projects.
为筹资中国基础设施项目而无中生有。
And that's what banks are allowed to do.
这就是银行可以做的事。
They're allowed to print money, create money out of nothing.
他们可以无中生有地印钞、造钱。
Okay. Does that make sense? Now the question
好的。这样说通吗？现在的问题是，等一下。
then is, wait a minute here.
那就先等一下。
That's kind of absurd. How this system come into being?
这有点荒谬。这个系统是怎么出现的？
How is it created? Okay. Well, actually, there's a very easy explanation for
它是怎么创建的？好的。其实有个很简单的解释，说明我们是怎么得到这个系统的。
where we got the system from.
好的。接下来让我来解释一下这个系统的历史和起源。
All right. So let me explain the history and the origin of the system.
So in the beginning, it was merchants
于是最初，商人们才是主角
who engaged in finance
他们从事金融业务
because merchants needed money in order to facilitate trade.
因为商人需要资金来促成交易
And some merchants became extremely wealthy.
有些商人变得极其富有。
And when they became very wealthy,
当他们变得非常富有时，
they started banks in order to support China.
他们便创办银行以支撑中国。
And so they started to trade in other merchants. Okay.
于是他们开始与其他商人进行贸易。好的。
So these banks traded in gold
于是这些银行以金进行贸易
because that was the primary source
因为金是主要来源
and supply of money back then.
并在那时再补给钱。
Okay. So what happened is
好的。所以发生的事是
you would come and you would put your money,
你会来，然后你会把钱放进去。
your gold in a bank for safekeeping.
把你的黄金存入银行保管。
And the bank would give you a contract.
银行会给你一份合同。
All right. A contract is just saying,
好的。合同就是这么说，
thank you for giving me your gold.
谢谢你给我的黄金。
I promise to give back your gold at any time that you want it.
我保证随时归还你的黄金。
And this is what we call a receipt, right?
这就是我们所说的收据，对吧？
And this would allow for better
并且这将使更好
and easier trade because
而且更易交易因为
now I can take this contract and I can go to England.
现在我可以拿着这份合同去英格兰
Okay. Maybe I'm based in Italy, but
好的。也许我在意大利，但现在我可以去英格兰并说，听着，我需要从你那里买棉花或香蕉。
now I can go to England and said, listen, I need to buy
现在我可以去英格兰并说，听着，我需要从你那里买棉花或香蕉。
cotton or bananas from you.
And the person was like, well, what do you give me?
于是那人说，嗯，你给我什么？
I'm going to give you gold. Right.
我会给你黄金。对吧。
So I take the receipt and I give it to you.
于是我拿着收据递给你。
Right. And why do we, and why do we do this?
对了，那我们为什么要这么做呢？
Because it's a lot easier than giving gold to other people.
因为比把黄金给别人更简单。
And so this system would facilitate trade throughout the world.
这样一来，整个系统就能促进全球贸易。
Does it make sense? Now I'm the bank.
它有意义吗？现在我是银行。
I have all this gold and I want to make money with it.
我手里有这么多黄金，想靠它赚钱。
So I want to give it to other people.
于是我想把它给别人。
So other merchants would come to me and say, listen, I need gold.
于是其他商人会来找我说，听着，我需要黄金。
Can you lend me out gold?
你能借给我黄金吗？
Right. But
对了。
I say to him, yeah, but if I give you out the gold,
我对他说，好的，但如果我把黄金给你，你就有安全问题。
you have a security issue.
这对你不方便。那我为什么不把黄金给你呢。
It's inconvenient for you. So why don't I give you a gold?
It's inconvenient for you. Sowhy don't I give you a gold?
Why don't you give me a receipt, a contract instead?
为什么不给我一张收据，一份合同呢？
Does that make sense? Because all I need is a contract.
这样说对吗？因为我只需要一份合同。
All I need is a receipt in order to go and do trade elsewhere.
我只需要一张收据，才能去别处做交易。
Right. So, so by doing this,
好的。于是，做完这件事后，
what I've done is I've doubled
我所做的就是把我的金子翻倍了。
the gold in my bank.
在我的银行里，金子翻倍了。
Right. I've created money out of nothing.
好的。我凭空创造了钱。
So the gold is still 5 million.
于是，金子还是五百万。
That hasn't changed, but the receipt is now 5 million plus 5 million.
那没变，但收据现在是5百万加5百万。
So theoretically, I now have 10 million in the bank.
于是，理论上我现在在银行里有一千万。
All right. So that's how money
好的，那就是这么回事。
and finance works.
和金融运作。
Now there's a problem with the system.
现在系统出现问题。
What's the problem with the system? What do you mean?
系统有什么问题？你说的是什么？
Why would he have to say the receipt has gold as the same amount of...
他为什么要说收据里有金子，和同样的金额…
Okay. That's a good question. Okay.
好的。那是个好问题。好的。
Why is it that people believe in me?
人们为什么会相信我？
Okay. The answer is very simple.
好的。答案很简单。
The answer is because for most of you of human history, people didn't need money.
答案是因为在大多数人类历史里，人们不需要钱。
If you, if you were just a normal person, what were you doing?
如果你，假设你只是普通人，你在做什么？
Were you in a village growing crops?
你是在村里种田吗？
If you wanted to like get new stuff, what would you do?
如果你想买新东西，你会怎么做？
You would trade with someone else, right?
你会和别人交换，对吧？
Maybe, maybe you have a gold that I want.
也许，你手里有我想要的黄金。
Well then I would trade you a cow for it.
那我就把一头牛换给你吧。
So we didn't actually need money.
于是我们其实不需要钱。
So for most of human history,
所以在大多数人类历史里，
no one had any need for money.
没有人需要钱。
It was only in certain circumstances that you would want money.
只有在特定情形下才会想要钱。
So for example, marriage, right?
比如说结婚，对吧？
Okay. So for most of human history,
好的。于是在人类历史的大多数里，
money represented...
钱代表着……
Debt that could be unpaid.
债务永远无法偿还。
Oh, sorry. Debt that could never be repaid.
哦，抱歉。债务永远无法偿还。
So for example, a very common thing is maybe you
比如说，一个很常见的情形是你……
and I fight and I kill you.
我打架，我杀了你。
Well, in theory,
好吧，理论上，
your family should not come and kill me, but obviously that would create a lot of problems, right?
你的家族应该不会来杀我，但显然这会造成不少麻烦，对吧？
So the way to settle the dispute is I would give your family money.
解决争端的办法是我给你家族钱。
Because money was symbolically meant to say,
因为钱象征性地表示，
I'm sorry, I killed you.
我很抱歉，我杀了你。
This is a debt that can never be repaid.
这是一笔永远偿不完的债。
Right? That's what money was used for in most circumstances throughout human history.
对吧？这就是钱在历史上大多数情况下的用途。
There was no actually real use for money.
钱本身并没有实际用途。
It was symbolic. But with the rise of trade,
它是象征性的。但随着贸易的兴起，
there were merchants, they needed money in order to facilitate the trade.
有商人，他们需要钱来促进贸易。
But these merchants all knew each other.
这些商人彼此相识。
So they trusted each other.
于是他们彼此信任。
And they trusted each other. And they trusted each other anyway. So
他们彼此相识，彼此相信。于是……
money was a mechanism for
钱是一个机制，……
them to trade easier.
让他们更容易交易。
Okay? Does that make sense? All right.
好的？那有道理吗？好了。
Okay. So let's go back to the question.
好的。那我们回到问题上来。
This system looks great.
这个系统看起来不错。
I can print money out of nothing.
我可以凭空印钱。
But there's a problem with this system.
但这个系统有个问题。
What is the problem? There's a problem here.
问题是什么？这里有个问题。
Hmm?.
嗯？
. Okay.
好的。
That's actually a great question. Okay? So yeah.
这实际上是个很好的问题。好的？那就这样。
Is it possible to forge the contract?
可以伪造合同吗？
Okay? So that's a really good point.
好的？这真是个好点子。
The problem is...
问题是……
So the answer is that they all knew each other anyway.
于是答案是，他们彼此都已相识。
Okay? Because it's a very small circle.
好吧？因为圈子很小。
Again, we have not reached the modern period where
再说，我们还未到现代时期。
it's a lot of people using money.
有很多人用钱。
If that's the case, then fortune becomes a problem.
如果是这样，财富就成了问题。
We'll discuss this in future classes.
我们将在后续课上讨论。
Okay? Counterfeiting. But at this point in history, fortune is actually not a big issue.
好的？伪造。但在这段历史里，财富其实并不是大问题。
There's actually a bigger issue. And it's a huge issue.
其实有更大的问题。那是个大问题。
What's the issue? All right.
问题是什么？好了。
$5 million of gold, right?
$500万的黄金，对吧？
There's about $10 million of gold out there in receipts.
大约有1000万的黄金在收据里。
What's the problem with that?.
那有什么问题呢？
. The problem is that if everyone wants the gold at the same time,
问题是如果大家同时想要黄金
I go bankrupt, right?
我破产了，对吧？
Because I lose my reputation. The contract says that
因为我失去声誉。合同写着这样
at any time you want the gold, I must give it to you.
在任何你想要黄金的时刻，我必须交给你。
But if I have like...
但如果我有……
If there's $100 million in gold contracts,
如果有一亿美元的黄金合约，
but I only have $10 million in gold,
但我只有一千万美元的黄金。
only if $15 million wants the gold back,
只有当1,500万美元想要黄金时，我才会被搞砸。
then I'm screwed. This is what we call a bank run.
这就是我们所说的银行挤兑。
Okay? A bank run. And
好的？银行挤兑。还有
this is a huge problem for merchants.
这对商人来说是个大问题。
Okay? There's also another problem with this system.
好的？这个系统还有另一个问题。
And the problem is this. Who
问题是这样的。谁
do I usually lend my money to?
我通常把钱借给谁？
Do you guys know? If I'm a bank, if I'm a merchant, who do I usually lend my money to?
你们知道吗？如果我是银行，如果我是商人，我通常把钱借给谁？
. Okay, guys.
好的，大家。
Today, we lend the money to our subscribers.
今天，我们把钱借给我们的订阅者。
Ubuntu.
Ubuntu。
the king would be like,
国王会是这样，像是……
screw you bank, I don't need to pay you back.
把你们的银行搞砸，我不需要还钱。
Okay? So there's actually a lot of risk with this system.
好的？所以这个系统实际上有很多风险。
So over time,
于是，随着时间的推移，
develop a system to mitigate or reduce this risk.
他们会发展出一种系统来缓解或降低这种风险。
Okay? What they would do is they would create cartels.
他们会做的就是创建卡特尔。
Cartels are just partnerships.
卡特尔只是合作关系。
So maybe this bank works with another bank,
所以这家银行可能与另一家银行合作，
works with another bank throughout Europe.
在整个欧洲与另一家银行合作。
And the way they establish these cartels is usually through intermarriage, right?
他们通过联姻来建立这些卡特尔，没错吧？
They would marry each other. They would combine together.
他们互相结婚，合并在一起。
And that way,
于是这样，
let's say 15
让我们说15
million of receipts wants back the gold,
百万收据想要回金子，
but there's only 10 million. Well, guess what?
但只有10百万。好吧，猜猜？
You just go to another bank. Okay?
你只要去另一家银行。好吗？
And let's just say a king.
再说一个国王。
Decides, I'm not going to pay you back, bank. Well,
决定，我不再还钱给你，银行。好吧？
your bank works with other banks to establish a new
你的银行与其他银行合作，建立一个新的敌人，去杀掉国王以取回钱。
enemy to kill the king to get the money back.
你明白了吗？
Do you understand? And
this system is what we call today central banking.
这个系统就是我们今天所说的中央银行制度。
And what you will learn in this class is central banking controls the world today.
在这门课里你会学到，中央银行控制着今天的世界。
Okay? Now,
好了？现在，
what's really important about this system is
这套系统真正重要的是
that it's based on power.
它是基于力量的
Right? And what power is, you can turn nothing,
对吧？而力量是什么呢
money, the contract into everything.
钱，合同融入一切。
Right? That's what money is.
对吧？这就是钱的意义。
Okay. Okay. So we live in a world in
好了。好了。我们生活在一个世界里。
which banks can print out money.
哪家银行可以印出钱。
Right? So now let's ask ourselves the question.
对吧？现在让我们自己问个问题。
Wait a minute here.
等一下。
If the banks can print as much money as possible,
如果银行可以印出尽可能多的钱，
why do we have poverty?
那为什么我们还有贫困？
Right? Because we can just give money to poor people and they wouldn't be poor anymore.
对吧？因为我们可以把钱给穷人，他们就不再贫困了。
Why do we have poverty? Because we can just give money to poor people and they wouldn't be poor anymore.
为什么我们还有贫困？因为我们可以把钱给穷人，他们就不再贫困了。
Because we can just give money to poor people and they wouldn't be poor anymore. the world that we want, why are people starving still?
因为我们可以把钱给穷人，他们就不再贫困了。我们想要的世界，为什么人们仍在挨饿？
Why? Okay.
为什么？好的。
So we don't have limited resources.
于是我们就没有有限资源。
We have scarcity. Okay. Right.
我们有稀缺。好的。对。
So that is the common answer.
所以这就是常见答案。
Scarcity. We have poverty
稀缺。我们有贫困
because of scarcity, but I already told you this.
因为稀缺，但我已经告诉你了。
They can print money out of nothing.
他们可以凭空印钱。
So money is infinite.
钱是无限的。
Money is an infinite resource.
钱是一种无限资源。
So why are we, why do we have poor people then? That's kind of strange.
那为什么我们会有贫困的人呢？这有点奇怪。
You see
你看到了
what's happening is this.
正在发生的事就是这样。
You all believe money is scarce.
你们都认为钱是稀缺的。
Okay. Okay. I just spent the past 10, 20 minutes explaining to you.
好的。好的。我刚刚用十、二十分钟解释给你听。
It's not scarce. It's infinite.
它不是稀缺的，它是无限的。
It's just a number. We can at any time print out as much money as we need.
它只是一个数字。我们随时可以印出所需的金额。
Okay. So that's how power works.
好的。那就是权力的运作方式。
Power has brainwashed you into thinking something
权力让你脑中装上了一个不真实的想法。
that is not true.
这想法并不是真的。
You've been taught from the first day
从第一天起你就被教导，钱是稀缺的。
that money is scarce,
but it's not scarce.
但它并不稀缺。
It's infinite. And no matter what I say to you, it's not true.
它是无限的。无论我对你说什么，都是不对的。
It's not true. It's not true. It's not true. It's not true. It's not true. You still believe this. Okay.
它是这样才对的。它是这样才对的。它是这样才对的。它是这样才对的。它是这样才对的。你仍然相信。好了。
So you have to get that out of your head.
于是你得把它从脑子里拿出来。
Money is not scarce. It is infinite.
钱并不稀缺，它是无限的。
So let's work with a question.
于是我们用一个问题来展开。
Why is there poverty in this world?
为什么世界上有贫穷？
Why do people starve? Why is there inequality in this world?
为什么人们会挨饿？为什么世界上会有不平等？
Why are there poor people? Why are there rich people?
为什么有穷人？为什么有富人？
What's the answer? Because
答案是什么？因为
they don't print. Okay.
他们没印出来。好了。
Because it's scarce.
因为它很稀缺。
So guys, this is amazing.
所以各位，这太精彩了。
Okay. You guys can't get it out of your head.
好的，你们想不出来。
You think money's scarce.
你认为货币稀缺。
You think it is not possible to print infinite money
你认为可以印无限货币。
when I already told you it is possible to print infinite money because they do this all the time.
当我已经告诉你可以印无限货币，因为他们一直这么做。
Yeah? The one who
是吗？那个人是…
has the power don't want everyone to share the same...
有权力的人不想让大家共享同样的…
Yeah, because we don't want people to all have money.
是的，因为我们不想让大家都有钱。
The powerful people don't want that.
强者不想这样。
That's the exact answer. And why?
这就是答案。为什么呢？
Because otherwise no one would work. Do you understand?
否则没人会工作。你明白了吗？
The point of printing money is not to give you money.
印钱的要点不是给你钱。
The point of printing money is to create the illusion
印钱的要点是制造一种幻觉
that money is valuable and therefore
钱才是有价值的
you work hard in order to obtain it.
你努力工作以获得它。
But in order for me to make money,
但为了让我赚钱，
to make you want to get money,
让你想要得到钱。
I need to create artificial misery.
我需要制造人为的痛苦。
Do you understand? Right?
你明白了吗？对吧？
If there weren't poor people, you wouldn't want to be rich.
如果没有穷人，你就不会想要富裕。
It's only because you see people suffer that you would want to go make money for yourself.
只有看到人们受苦，你才会想为自己赚钱。
What do your parents tell you? Your parents tell you work hard in school, make a lot of money.
你父母会说：努力读书，赚大钱。
Otherwise, you're gonna end up like a poor person.
不然你就会像穷人一样。”
Right? Well, guess what?
对吧？那你猜怎么回事？
If there are no poor people, your parents couldn't say that to you.
如果没有穷人，你父母就不会这么说。
And you wouldn't want to work hard in school.
你也就不会想在学校努力读书。
Right? That's why we have poverty.
对吧？这就是我们有贫困的原因。
Because poverty creates the illusion that money is valuable.
因为贫困让人们产生钱才有价值的错觉。
In other words, poverty isn't what you do to yourself,
换句话说，贫困不是你对自己的所作所为。
it is what the powerful do to you.
它是强者对你的所作所为。
Now let me ask you another question.
现在让我再问你一个问题。
You guys have studied some economics.
你们已经学过一些经济学了。
Why do you have like crises?
为什么你们会出现危机？
Crises. For example, there's a stock market crash.
危机。例如，股市崩盘。
Or for example, the economy goes down and people lose their jobs.
或者说，经济下行，人们失业。
Why do you have crises? I don't think.
为什么你们会出现危机？我想不通。
Exactly. You're not taught this in economics class.
完全正确。你们在经济课上没学过。
That's kind of weird, right? The point of crises is to destroy money.
这有点奇怪，吧？危机的要点是毁钱。
Why do we need to destroy money? Because if there's too much money in the stock market,
为什么我们要销毁钱？因为如果股市里钱太多，
in the system, people don't have to work.
系统里人就不必工作。
So you have to destroy this money in order to make people feel money is scarce.
于是你们就得销毁钱，让人们觉得钱稀缺。
Okay, does that make sense? So why do we have wars?
好的，听得懂吗？那为什么我们会有战争？
Right? Why are there wars in the world then?
对吧？那世界上为什么会有战争？
Because they're fighting over scarce resources, right?
因为他们在争夺稀缺资源，对吧？
I already told you. Scarcity is a lie.
我已经告诉你了。稀缺是谎言。
The real reason is war is meant to destroy wealth.
真正的原因是战争是用来消灭财富的。
In order to make you think money is valuable.
让你们觉得钱有价值。
Do you understand? You guys play World of Warcraft?
你明白了吗？你们玩《魔兽世界》吗？
Or these games, right? Guess what, guys?
或者玩这些游戏，对吧？猜猜看，伙计们？
World of Warcraft, in our world, there's actually no difference.
《魔兽世界》在我们世界里，其实无二者。
You just run around pointlessly, working hard to obtain credits in order to buy stuff.
你只是在无目的地跑来跑去，努力赚取积分以买东西。
If credits just flew out of the sky, because they could do that, right?
如果积分能从天上掉下来，因为他们可以做到，没错吧？
They could actually program the engine to just put money out of nothing,
他们实际上可以把引擎编程成随便生成积分。
you wouldn't do nothing every day.
你每天都不会什么都不做。
You wouldn't play the game. Right?
你不会玩游戏。对吧？
Okay? It's only because you believe
好吧？只是因为你相信。
that there's scarcity in the world
世界上有稀缺，必须努力工作才能获得财富。
and that you must work hard to obtain wealth
你必须努力工作才能得到财富。
that you do any work. Do you understand this?
你做任何工作都要努力。
Okay? So this world that we live in,
好的？我们生活的这个世界，
it's a complete illusion
它是完全的幻觉，
created by central banking in order to
由中央银行创造的，
make us work as hard as possible.
让我们尽可能努力工作。
Because the real value is not money.
因为真正的价值不在于金钱。
The real value is the work we do. There's only
真正的价值是我们所做的工作。
Ubuntu Ubuntu
乌班图
Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu
乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图
Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu
乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图
Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu
乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图
Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu Ubuntu question okay
乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图 乌班图
so the question is isn't food scarce because
所以问题是：食物不稀缺吗？
food is a finite resource right do
食物是有限资源，对吧？
yourself a favor okay go to the
给自己一个小忙，去北京的垃圾堆里找找
garbage dump somewhere anywhere in beijing and
garbage dump somewhereanywhere in beijing and
see the amount of food that
看一下食物的量
is wasted every single day if food was scarce why do we have food waste
每天都有食物被浪费，如果食物稀缺，为什么还会有浪费？
okay so if you just do the mathematics what you will
好的，那如果你只做数学，你会得到什么
discover is there's enough food to
发现有足够的食物可以
feed everyone okay it doesn't have to be hunger and
给大家吃饭，没必要是饥饿
starvation it's an artificial crisis it doesn't make sense
饥饿是人为的危机，毫无意义
so you're right in that yeah the food is not infinite but
所以你说得对，食物不是无限的
it's abundant there's a lot of it
它很丰富，数量很多
enough to feed people okay okay
足够供人吃饭，好的，好的
okay okay all right um
好的，好的，没问题
so again you guys are stuck in the scarcity mindset um
于是你们又陷入了稀缺心态，嗯
and it's very convincing so
而且这点很有说服力
let's move on okay
好了，继续吧
so this is this is something that
这就是……
we'll go back to later on okay because
我们稍后再回到这点，好的，因为
i cannot convince you today this morning that
今天早上我还说不服你
everything you believed about the world about yourself is
你对世界、对自己的所有认知都已是错的，嗯你仍然停留在那种稀缺心态，嗯。
wrong okay you're still stuck there like okay there's scarcity um
and you're right there's scarcity but
而你说的没错，确实有稀缺，但……
we also live in a world of abundance okay and a lot of things
我们也生活在一个充满的世界里，嗯，很多事物都充足了
that you believe are just misconceptions about the world okay
你认为的只是关于世界的误解，好的
so so we'll go back there okay later on all right so
于是我们稍后再回到那点，好的，全部都明白了，嗯
let's move on okay so
好了，接着说，好的
we've done money now right now let's do another
我们已经谈过钱了，现在再来一个
question let's do a question of happiness
再来一个关于幸福的问题
the question
问题
for us today is what makes us happy
今天对我们来说，是什么让我们快乐？
come on what makes you happy how can you live a happy life
来吧，是什么让你快乐？你怎样才能过上快乐的生活？
well obviously money right you have a lot
嗯，显然是钱，对吧，你有很多钱。
of money that's gonna make you happy what else
钱的事能让你开心，还有什么？
exactly power right sure power
正是权力，对吧，权力。
excuse me freedom okay
请问自由呢？
good freedom yeah what
好的，自由，嗯，什么？
else relationships yep sure
还有什么？关系，嗯，好的。
you have good friends right like lots and lots of friends what else
你有好朋友，对吧，很多很多朋友，还有什么？
okay love right love sure what
好的，爱吧，爱，没错，爱，嗯？
else like video games i guess
还有什么？比如视频游戏，我猜吧？
vacations okay lots and
假期，好多了
lots of things okay what you will discover about this list is this
好多事，好的，你会发现这份清单的内容是这样的：
you are thinking about individuals you are thinking about people you are thinking about people you are thinking about people you are thinking about people happiness
你在想个体，你在想人，你在想人，你在想人，你在想人，幸福。
and this is actually unique in human history
这点实际上在人类历史上是独一无二的。
if you if you go back in time to five five years ago
如果你回到五年前
and
然后
you ask people how can you be
你问人们怎么做
happy they would focus more
他们会更专注
on collective happiness in other words if your community is happy you're going to be happy
在其他方面就是如果你的社区开心，你也会开心
same same
同样同样
same same same same same same same same same same same
同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样
same same same same same same same same same same same same same
同样同样
same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same
same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same same
同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同
same same same same same same same same same same
同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样
same same same same same same same same Happiness meant helping others,
同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同样同
being generous to others.
对他人慷慷大方
So for example, let's just say
比如说
that I go off
于是我走了
and I wonder and then I find a lot of gold, right?
我想想，然后我发现很多金子，对吧？
I come back and what's the first thing I do with all this gold?
我回来了，先把这堆金子做什么？
Do you guys know? And this is like the ancient past.
你们知道吗？这就是古代的做法。
Dig a hole and put them inside.
挖个坑，把钱放进去。
Okay, yeah, good, right?
好的，行吧，对吗？
We're gonna dig a hole and put that money inside because we wanna give to our children.
我们要挖个坑，把钱放进去，给孩子们用。
That's a modern mindset. But what did they do before?
那是现代心态。那之前他们做了什么？
And this happened throughout every society.
这在各个社会都发生过。
If I became rich one day, what's the first thing I would do?
如果我有一天变得很富有，我第一件事会做什么？
Show off? Hmm?
炫耀？嗯？
Show off? No, okay, so we'll learn this, okay?
炫耀？不，好的，那我们来学这个，行吗？
But the first thing that people did was they had a big feast for everyone.
但人们最先做的事是给大家办一场大宴会。
They spent all the money on a big feast.
他们把所有的钱都花在了一场大宴会上。
Because what mattered was, your reputation within the community.
因为重要的是，你在社区里的声誉。
What mattered was your generosity.
重要的是你的慷慨。
If you got rich one day, you made sure that
如果你有一天变得很富有，你会确保……
everyone in the community benefited from your wealth,
社区里的每个人都能从你的财富中受益。
usually by holding a big feast.
通常通过办一场大宴会来完成。
And guess what, guys? This is true in China for most of Chinese history,
你们猜怎么回事？这在中国大部分历史里都是真的，right?
right?
If you come from a Chinese village, come to Beijing,
如果你来自中国的一个小村庄，来到北京，
you open a restaurant, you make a lot of money, you go out to your village, what's the first thing you do?
你开了一家餐馆，赚了很多钱，回到自己的村庄，第一件事是什么？
Come on, guys. You have a big feast for everyone.
来吧，伙计们。你给大家办一场大宴会。
Okay, so this is ingrained in us, okay?
好的，这已经根深蒂固在我们心里了，明白吗？
But as you say, today, what we believe is,
正如你所说，今天我们所信的是，
if you have a lot of money, put it underground or put it in a bank, okay?
如果你有很多钱，放进地下或存进银行，明白吗？
But back then, for most of human history, we would just spend it all on a big feast.
但那时，几乎人类历史的那段时间里，我们只会把钱全部花在一场大宴会上。
We wanted everyone to share in happiness, and that's what made us happy,
我们想让大家一起共享喜悦，这就是让我们开心的原因，行吗？
okay?
Any questions? Yeah?
还有问题吗？嗯？
I was wondering, you mentioned that
我在想，你刚才说过
it was for reputation on some levels.
它在某些层面上是关于声誉的。
Would that count into as individual happiness?
那算作个人幸福吗？
Because after you get rich, you care about your reputation.
因为你一富起来就会在乎自己的声誉。
Okay, yeah, so you're asking, is this about individual reputation?
好的，回到问题：这关乎个人声誉吗？
And again, I mean, this is hard, okay?
再说一次，我是说这很难，行吗？
But the individual reputation is not about the individual, the concept of individual did not exist before.
但个人声誉不是关于个人，个人的概念在之前还不存在。
We just created it.
我们刚刚才创造了它。
The idea that I'm a person independent of my family, independent of my community,
我独立于家族、社区、周遭世界的想法毫无意义。
independent of the world around me, makes no sense.
过去对你最严重的惩罚是什么？
What was the worst punishment that could be inflicted on you in the past?
Let's just say that we're gonna fight, I kill you, right?
我们就说吧，咱们要打了，我会杀了你，对吧？
You're, they say you are no longer belong to this world.
你啊，他们说你已经不属于这个世界了。
Exactly, banishment, exile.
正是如此，流放，流放。
You're, they say you are no longer belong to this world. death, right? And today, if I killed you, the police would come catch me and then kill me.
你啊，他们说你已经不属于这个世界了。死亡，对吧？今天如果我杀了你，警察就会来抓我，然后再杀我。
But before, we didn't do that because the worst thing
但之前我们没这么做，因为最糟的事是把你流放。
that we could do was exile you.
我们能做的最糟的事就是把你流放。
It says, you're no longer part of us.
它说，你已经不再是我们的一部分。
You understand? So the concept of individuality did not exist,
你明白吗？所以个体的概念并不存在，
right?
对吧？
Okay, so let's move on.
好的，接下来继续。
All right, so
好的，开始吧。
now I'm going to present two understandings of the world
现在我要给出两种对世界的理解
and you're going to tell me which understanding you think is correct.
你要告诉我哪一种理解是正确的
And the first understanding,
第一种理解是，
we humans don't have agency.
我们人类没有主导权。
We don't have really control. Why?
我们真的没有控制。为什么？
Because there are powerful gods out there, okay?
因为外面有强大的神啊，行吗？
There are these powerful gods like Apollo,
有这些强大的神，如阿波罗，多尼修斯。
Dionysus.
Oh, the problem though is that
哦，问题在于
they are also controlled by other gods that are more powerful, like for example, fate.
它们也被更强大的神控制，例如命运。
Fortune. And
命运。然后
then there are these really ancient gods
接着有这些非常古老的神
that control the structure of the universe.
它们掌控宇宙结构。
For example, maybe anger and pride.
例如，愤怒与自负。
So you obviously know individual agency
所以你显然知道个体行动。
because there's always a god screwing with you, okay?
因为总有神在玩弄你，行吗？
You might get rich, but then
你可能会富有，但随后
the god of pride looks at you and says, no, no, no.
自负之神看着你说，没，没，没。
I need to teach this mortal a lesson.
我得给这凡人上一课。
So you're not going to control the world. The god comes into me,
于是你就不会去掌控世界。神会降临我身，令我自负，随后我就搞砸了，行吗？
makes me too arrogant, and I screw up, okay?
于是我们总是被这些超出我们理解的力量所控制。
So we're always being controlled by these forces beyond our understanding.
我们是神经，产生记忆，行吗？
Okay, so that's the first worldview.
好的，那就是第一个世界观。
The second worldview is this.
第二个世界观是这个。
We are synapses that
我们是突触。
generate memories,
生成记忆，
okay?
行吗？
We are memories.
我们是记忆。
Okay? We are memories. Our understanding is that we are synapses that generate memories. Our understanding of the world comes from our experience.
好的？我们是记忆。我们的理解是我们是产生记忆的突触。我们对世界的理解来自我们的经验。
That is controlled by synapses.
那是由突触控制的。
Synapses come from a combination of DNA
突触来自DNA的组合。
and environment.
和环境。
Our genes and our interaction with the environment, our experiences.
我们的基因与与环境的互动，我们的经历。
And what this means is that
这意味着的事是：
we can now have control over our own individual fate.
我们现在可以掌控自己的命运。
If you're angry, it's because some experience is not going to control you.
如果你生气，那是因为某些经历不再掌控你。
So we're not going to control you. There's someone being Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub
于是我们不再掌控你。有人在掌控着。
Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub
乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌布乌
Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub
Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub
Ub Ub
乌布乌布
Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub Ub there are lots
有很多
and lots of gods, they're evil and
还有许多神祇，它们是邪恶的
they're random and
它们是随机的，并且
we have absolutely no control over our fate.
我们完全没有掌控命运的能力。
We can only hope to get lucky in life and not piss off the gods.
我们只能祈祷人生顺遂，免得惹神怒
In the second worldview,
在第二个世界观中，
we are only a collection of our memories
我们只是记忆的集合
and we are only synopsis.
而我们只是梗概。
So we're able to manipulate the memories and
于是我们可以操纵记忆并
the synopsis in a proper way,
以正确的方式梗概，
we can be free of all problems.
我们可以摆脱所有问题。
We can be free of anger, we can be free of depression,
我们可以摆脱愤怒，我们可以摆脱抑郁，
we can be free of misery.
我们可以摆脱苦难
All right? Let me ask you this question.
好的？让我问你一个问题。
Which worldview is a more accurate reflection of reality?
哪种世界观更准确地反映了现实？
Obviously the second one, right? Because
显然是第二个，对吧？因为
this is neuroscience.
这就是神经科学。
So, science or psychology or psychiatry.
所以，科学、心理学或精神病学。
This is what you've been taught in school.
这就是你们在学校里学到的内容。
This is what you all believe.
这就是你们都相信的事。
Our entire society is structured around this very idea.
我们的整个社会都围绕这个想法来构建。
And what you will learn in this class is it is completely wrong.
而你在这门课里学到的内容完全是错的。
It is the first one that is more accurate reflection of reality.
第一种说法更准确地反映了现实。
The first one gives you more information,
第一句给你更多信息，
gives you a more accurate assessment of how the world really works.
第二句给你更准确的评估，说明世界真正运作的方式。
Okay? So now let me ask you this question.
好的？现在让我问你这个问题。
In the first worldview, and
在第一种世界观中，
this is what we call polytheism.
这就是我们所说的多神论。
And polytheism for most of human history was the dominant religion.
而在大多数人类历史中，多神论是主导宗教。
Okay? Now we live in a world where the religion is science.
好吧？现在我们生活在一个宗教就是科学的世界里。
Science is basically religion. So,
科学基本上就是宗教。所以，
why did we make the transition?
我们为什么做了这个转变？
What's the benefit? If you're a powerful person, what would you prefer?
有什么好处？如果你是个有权势的人，你会更倾向什么？
The second one as opposed to the first one?
第二个与第一个相对吗？
Why? What's the benefits to powerful people?
为什么？对有权势的人有什么好处？
What is power?
什么是权力？
Why do you believe the second one but not the first one?
你为什么相信第二个而不是第一个？
They can blame you on failure and blame on fault.
他们会把失败和过错都怪在你身上。
Yeah, okay. Okay, so
好，好的。
the idea of individual responsibility.
个体责任的概念。
Okay? So then there's more control.
好的？于是就有更多控制。
It's easier to control people in the system.
在系统中更容易掌控人们。
Right? That's the first benefit.
对吗？那就是第一个好处。
What's the second benefit? The second benefit is you will work harder, right?
第二个好处是什么？第二个好处是你会更努力工作，对吗？
Because in the first system, you're like, you know what?
因为在第一个系统里，你就像……你知道吗？
I don't need to go make a lot of money because
我不需要去赚很多钱，因为
if I make a lot of money,
如果我赚了很多钱
the gods will punish me and make me proud.
神们会惩罚我并让我自豪。
So I'm just going to like enjoy life and take it easy.
所以我就想好好享受生活，轻松一点。
Right? So in the second system,
对吧？所以在第二个系统里，
no, no, I have control over my own life.
不，不，我可以掌控自己的生活。
So I need to work hard. Okay?
所以我需要努力工作。好吗？
So again, the entire point of the system is to make you work as hard as possible
所以，整个系统的要点就是让你尽可能努力工作。
because when you work hard, that generates real wealth for the powerful people.
因为努力工作会为强者创造真正的财富。
Money does nothing. Okay?
钱什么也不做。好吗？
Money just incentivizes you to work hard.
钱只是激励你努力工作。
So this exists in order to make you work harder.
所以它的存在就是为了让你更努力工作。
There's one more benefit or there's more benefits, but what's another benefit?
还有一个好处，或者说还有更多好处，但另一个好处是什么？
The other benefit is this.
另一个好处是这个。
Powerlessness. Okay?
无力感。好吗？
Powerlessness. It makes you powerless.
无力感。它让你变得无力。
Why? This system is designed to make you absolutely powerless.
为什么？这个系统就是要让你完全无力。
Why? You can't control anything.
为什么？你什么都控制不了。
Why? Everything is controlled by gods and fate.
为什么？一切都由神与命运掌控。
No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
不
See, see again, again, this is how you're brainwashed.
看，再看，再看，这就是你被洗脑的方式。
You believe one makes you powerless, but that's not correct.
你认为一是让你变成无力的。
Two makes you powerless. Why?
二让你无力。为什么？
What's the difference between one and two?
一和二有什么区别？
Why is it in number two? Number two, you are powerless.
为什么是二？二，你无力。
You're playing the game that the, uh,
你在玩那个游戏，呃，
who has the power wants you to be powerless.
谁有权力就想让你无力。
Okay. So
好的。
the problem with number two is you are incapable of collective action
问题在于二，你缺乏集体行动的能力
because
因为
you think all sorts of your problems is the individual in you and that society.
你认为所有问题都来自你自己和社会。
But number one, you are capable of collective action
但一号，你有集体行动的能力。
and the only way to change the world is through collective action.
而改变世界的唯一方式就是集体行动。
Does that make sense? This is a really important point.
这样说通吗？这点非常重要。
Two is designed to make you think the source of all your problems is within you.
二号设计让你认为所有问题的根源在于你自己。
So you should ignore what other people do and think.
于是你应该忽略他人所作所为，专注于思考。
It doesn't matter to you.
这点对你没意义。
And therefore you're incapable of identifying with other people.
于是你无法与他人产生共识。
You're not capable of collective action.
你没有集体行动的能力。
You're not capable of collective action and you feel really miserable.
你没有集体行动的能力，且感到非常难过。
You're not capable of collective action. What you will do is play video
你没有集体行动的能力。你接下来会做的事是玩视频游戏或整天看黄片。
games or watch porn all day.
Okay. And that's what's happening in society today.
好的。那就是今天社会里正在发生的事。
Yeah. But in number two, like from experience,
是的。但在第二点，像经验那样，
we would know that you should listen to the other's advice or,
我们会知道你应该听取别人的建议，或者说，你应该采纳别人的视角。
you know, you should take others' perspectives
and not just...
并且不只是…
So in number two, who has authority?
于是第二点，谁有权威？
Who do you listen to? You listen to scientists,
你听谁的？你听科学家。
right? Scientists.
对吗？科学家。
Because this system was created by scientists to trick you.
因为这个系统是科学家们创造的，专门用来骗你的。
Okay. This system you think, oh, it's science.
好的。你认为这个系统是科学的。
Therefore it must be real.
因此它一定是…
Guys, let me give you a piece of advice.
各位，给你们一句小建议。
Okay. If you're ever feeling sad and
好的。如果你有时感到悲伤
you are depressed,
你很沮丧，
what should you do?
你该怎么做？
What should you do? What have you been taught to do?
你该怎么做？你又被教会做什么？
You feel sad, you're depressed,
你感到悲伤，你很沮丧，
what should you do? Go to the nature.
去大自然
Hmm? Walk around.
嗯？走走吧。
Okay. Yeah. The correct answer is walk around.
好的。对，正确答案就是走走吧。
But that's not what you've been taught, right? What have you been taught to do?
但这不是你被教会做的事，对吗？你又被教会做什么？
Telling your friend to your parent.
把你的朋友告诉给你的父母。
Okay. Telling your friend to your parent.
好的。把你的朋友告诉给你的父母。
That's actually really good, right?
这其实真的很好，对吗？
So walking around, exercising,
走走、锻炼、休息、跟朋友聊聊自己的问题。
resting, talking to a friend about your problem.
That's all really good. But what have you been taught to do in school?
那也都很好。那你在学校学会做什么？
Yeah. Really? If you are feeling really, really sad, what should you do?
是吗？如果你真的很难过，应该怎么做？
You should go talk to a psychiatrist, right?
你应该去找精神科医生，对吧？
You should talk to a psychologist.
你应该去找心理学家。
And what will he do? What will he or she do?
那他会做什么？他或她会做什么？
Okay. Well, I'm going to give you a piece of advice, okay?
好的。好了，我要给你一句建议，好吗？
And you can test it out for yourself. But if you're feeling sad and
你可以自己试试。只要你感到难过，且觉得自己需要去找精神科医生。
you are feeling depressed and you feel you have to talk to a psychiatrist
你感到沮丧，觉得自己需要去找精神科医生。
and you do so, I will make you bet
并且你这么做，我会让你押注
that the psychiatrist will make it a lot worse.
精神科医生会让情况更糟
You will feel worse after talking to a psychiatrist.
你会在去看精神科医生后感觉更糟。
Okay? And
好的？
the reason why is the system is
原因是系统的设定
not designed to cure you of any problems.
并非要治愈你的问题
The system is to make you dependent on authority.
系统的作用是让你依赖于权威。
You know that if you feel sad, well, you know what?
你知道如果你感到悲伤，那就……你知道是什么吗？
Just go for a walk, talk to a friend.
去散步，跟朋友聊聊。
You'll feel better over time. But the system teaches you, no, if you feel sad,
时间一长，你会感觉好些。
go talk to a psychiatrist who will give you drugs.
去找精神科医生给你开药。
It's designed to make you dependent on authority.
它的设计是让你依赖于权威。
Yeah? I want to ask,
是吗？我想问……
like, in scenario one, in world number one,
像，在情景一，世界一中，
wouldn't God also be an authority?
不就是上帝也会是权威吗？
Like, God would also be an authority?
像，上帝也会是权威吗？
That's actually a great question, okay? God is authority.
这真是个好问题，好的？上帝是权威。
Okay. That's actually a great question.
好的。这真是个好问题。
Thank you so much. So, I have to spend time to explain to you both systems.
谢谢你。于是，我得花时间向你解释这两套系统。
And I will do so. But
我也会这么做。但
what's really important about number
关于第一种的真正重要的是
one is the
gods are really
神真的很……
bad people.
是好人。
Okay? The gods in number one, the polytheistic system, they fight all the time.
好的？第一种的神，泛神论体系的神，他们一直在打仗。
They're vengeful.
他们是报复的。
They're angry. They're proud.
他们愤怒，骄傲。
But because they're gods, they can get away with it.
但因为是神，他们可以逃脱。
And that's the difference between humans and gods.
这就是人类与神的区别。
We're all the same. We're all angry.
我们都一样，都是愤怒的。
We're all jealous.
我们都嫉妒的。
We all fight, okay?
我们都在战斗，好吗？
But the gods can get away with it.
但神能逃脱。
The humans cannot. Gods can do hubris.
人类不能。神能自负。
We cannot do hubris. You understand?
我们不能自负。你明白吗？
So, the idea that, oh,
于是，那个想法，哦，
the people in power are benevolent,
掌权的人是仁慈的。
the people in power are authority figures who
掌权的人是权威人物，他们……
are after our best interests, that is a new modern concept.
他们在乎我们的最佳利益，这才是新的现代概念。
Before, it was a society of this, this, this, this, this, this, this, this, this, this, this, assume that the king is a king.
以前是……这、这、这、这、这、这、这、这、这、这、这，假设国王是国王。
Why? Because he's favored by the gods.
为什么？因为他得到了众神的青睐。
It's not because he's a good person.
不是因为他是好人。
It's not because he's a just ruler. It's just because the gods like him for whatever reason.
不是因为他是个正直的君主，只是因为众神喜欢他，随缘而已。
But guess what? The gods give and the gods take.
但你猜怎么回事？神明赐予，神又收回。
Maybe today the king will rule us,
也许今天国王会统领我们，
but maybe five years from now he gets unlucky and the gods kill him.
也许五年后他不幸，神祸之。
Too bad. If you read Greek mythology, and we will do so in this class, okay?
太好了。如果你读过希腊神话，我们在这节课里也会读，行吗？
We'll go over into Greek civilization. We'll look at Oedipus.
我们会进入希腊文明。我们会看俄狄浦斯。
We'll look at Homer, the Iliad, okay?
我们来看看荷马的《伊利亚特》，好吗？
They talk about this all the time.
他们一直在谈这个。
Fate is something that you cannot control.
命运是你无法掌控的事物。
It's something that happens to you.
它是发生在你身上的事。
And therefore, you must live life to your best.
于是，你要把生活过得尽善尽美。
All right? So the difference is this.
好了？所以区别就在这里。
The difference is in number one,
差别在第一点，
they have a concept called eudaimonia.
他们有一个叫做eudaimonia的概念。
If you have no control over your fate,
如果你对命运没有掌控，
if things can happen to you tomorrow
如果明天会有事发生在你身上
that kill you, then
那杀死你的，然后
live your life to the best of your ability today.
今天把你的生活过得尽善尽美。
Seize the day. Be the best that you can be today.
把握住今天。成为今天最好的自己。
And that's how you win favor from the gods.
这就是你赢得众神青睐的方式。
Eudaimonia, what we call flourishing.
eudaimonia，即我们所说的繁荣。
The point of life is to live life to the best of your ability.
人生的要点是把生活过得尽善尽美。
And that's how you win favor from the gods. Live it to the best of your ability.
这就是你赢得众神青睐的方式。把它过得尽善尽美。
And that's why, guess what, guys?
这就是原因，猜猜看，伙计们？
The ancients, the Greeks, they were superior to us.
古人，希腊人，他们比我们更优秀。
If you read Greek literature, if you read Greek philosophy,
如果你读过希腊文学，如果你读过希腊哲学，
Plato, Homer, Aeschylus, Euboides, they were the best.
柏拉图、荷马、埃斯库罗斯、欧布多伊德，他们是最棒的。
Today, we suck.
如今我们才是吃瓜的。
Why? Because instead of eudaimonia, we have pleasure.
为什么？因为我们把eudaimonia换成了快乐。
Rather than flourish as creative people,
不再像创作型人那样繁荣，
we're like, how do I get to the top? How do I get to the top? How do I get to the top? How do I get to the top? How do I enjoy my life today?
我们就像在问：我怎么才能登顶？我怎么才能登顶？我怎么才能登顶？我怎么才能登顶？我今天怎么才能享受生活？
How do I not feel sad?
我怎么不感到悲伤？
Okay? So in the first system, even
好吧？所以在第一个系统里，虽然听起来我们没有控制，没能动手，
though it sounds like we have no control, we have no agency,
though it sounds like we haveno control, we have no agency,
but it inspires us to live to the best of our ability.
但它激励我们发挥最佳能力。
In the second system, we're like, oh, you have complete control over your life.
在第二个系统里，我们就像说：哦，你完全掌控自己的生活。
It enslaves us. Okay?
它使我们成为奴隶。好吧？
All right. Now,
好的。现在，
let's move on to the third and final example.
让我们继续到第三个也是最后一个例子。
And I know this is shocking.
我知道这很震撼。
I know this is surprising. But
我知道这很惊人。但
over the course of the semester,
在整个学期里，
I will give you enough evidence to convince you that this is all true.
我会给你足够的证据，让你相信这全是真的。
Okay? I'm just setting up the structure and the framework today.
好的？我今天只是把结构和框架搭好。
All right. Let's do now the school.
好了。现在来做学校的事。
Guys, why do we have school?
伙计们，学校为什么要开呢？
Why are we in school? Why?
我们为什么在学校？为什么？
Why are you here? What?
你们为什么在这里？什么？
Some place.
某个地方。
Learn and teach. Exactly.
学习与教学。正是如此。
Right. Learn. What else?
好的。学习。还有什么？
Yeah. To get the degree.
是的。拿到学位。
Okay? To get the degree.
好的？拿到学位。
Okay. To graduate.
好的。毕业。
What else? Knowledge.
还有什么？知识。
Yes. Yeah.
是的。好的。
Excuse me? Excuse me?
请问？请问？
I feel like give the power a chance to brainwash someone.
我想给力量一次洗脑的机会。
Brainwashing. Okay.
洗脑。好的。
Guess what, guys? The correct answer is brainwashing.
猜猜看，大家？正确答案是洗脑。
Everything else is a lie.
其余全是谎言。
All right. What do you do in the school?
好的。你在学校做什么？
You come to class.
你来上课。
You listen to a lecture. You read books.
你听讲座，读书。
right and then you and then you have to do a test and you have to write a paper
好的，然后你又要做测试，写论文
and then and then
然后又
the teacher gives you a grade that's how you learn right let me ask you this question
老师给你打分，这就是学习的方式，来问你个问题
then throughout most of human history how did we learn
然后在大部分人类历史里，我们是怎么学的？
if you become a doctor what did you do
如果你成为医生，你会做什么？
the answer is experience do it right
答案是经验，做对了就行。
let me ask you this question
让我问你个问题
let's say
设想一下
you're 12 years old you're a doctor okay there are two paths ahead of you the first path is you know what I'm just put you in a hospital
你12岁，已经是医生了，前面有两条路，第一条是我刚才说的那条路——你进一家医院
and you're gonna learn there for like 10 years someone's gonna mentor you someone's you're gonna be
然后你会在那里学习大约十年，别人会指导你，你会成为那个人的学徒，或许多是第一年你所做的事就是观察医生的工作。
that person's apprentice maybe the first year all you do is like
你会观察医生的工作。
watch the floor okay but you're gonna observe the doctor
and then eventually the doctor is going in to tell
然后最终医生会去告诉你
you how to treat patients okay that's
你如何治疗病人，好的，就是这样
the first system second system is you go to the best school in the world
第一套系统，第二套系统是你去世界上最好的学校
then you go to Harvard for undergraduate
然后你去哈佛大学读本科
then
然后
you go to Harvard Medical School the best medical school in
你去哈佛医学院，世界上最好的医学院
the world okay age 30 who's the better doctor number one or number two
世界，30岁，谁是更好的医生，第一位还是第二位？
obviously the first one right because
显然是第一位，对吧？
the second person the person who went to Harvard and
第二位是去哈佛的那个人
Harvard Medical School did not ever work in a hospital
哈佛医学院从未曾在医院工作
you understand now
你现在明白了
let me ask you another question in the first system do you
让我再问你一个问题：在第一系统里你是
have to be really really smart to be
必须非常非常聪明才能成为好医生
a good doctor you don't actually
你实际上不需要
anyone can be a doctor
任何人都能成为医生
in the first system anyone
在第一系统里任何人
we human beings are all born
我们人类一出生就具备学习任何事物的能力
the capacity to learn anything if you wanted to
如果你想学习
learn it right you'll be an engineer you'll be a lawyer
学会了就能当工程师、律师
if you want to be a doctor you'll be a
如果你想当医生就能当……
scientist you'll be anything okay just go find a mentor
科学家，随你想做就行，去找个导师吧
who
谁
can teach you how to do so and I guarantee you
能教你怎么做，我保证你会学会好做
that you will learn how to do it well and
that you will learnhow to do it well and
anyone can do this but
任何人都能做到，但…
instead we have a system of education in which
…我们有一套教育体系，…
we tell students you're smart
我们告诉学生，你们很聪明
you're stupid smart students go to good schools
你们是聪明的学生去好学校
and good universities and
去好大学
they get good jobs stupid students go wash dishes okay
他们得到好工作，笨蛋学生去洗碗
and that was not true for most of human history it's true today
并且这在大多数人类历史中并非如此，今天却是如此
but for most of you of human history you want to go
但在大多数人类历史中，你们想去学习时只需去找老师
learn something all you had to do was go find a teacher
学习某事，所要做的就是去找老师
and that teacher would teach you
并且那位老师会教你
and then you would learn it right
然后你就会学会它
so
于是
school is not a
学校不是一个
place to teach you how
用来教你怎样的地方
to learn a school doesn't teach you knowledge it doesn't do that
学校不教你知识，它不做这件事
a school is a place that
学校是一个让你脑洗的地方
brainwashes you okay now the question is
脑洗你，好的，现在问题是
what does it brainwash you in what
它用什么方式让你脑洗
would it brainwash you okay all right to answer
它会让你脑洗吗？好了，回答吧。
that I'm going to give you some history okay
我会给你讲一些历史。
we will do a lot of history in this class but
我们在这节课里会做很多历史。
I'm going to tell you the three societies that
我要给你讲三个最早实行义务教育的社会
first introduced mandatory
第一条是……
free public
第二条是……
schooling in the world okay the first is called Sparta
世界的学校化，第一种叫做斯巴达
okay Sparta was a small city -state in
斯巴达是古希腊的一个小城邦
Greece like three four thousand years or three thousand years ago
大约三千四百年前
and they had a new system in which
并且他们有一种新制度，孩子们从五六岁起就被送进学校
children as early as five or six years old they were put into a school
孩子们从五六岁起就被送进学校
and
in the school they were beaten up by older kids
在学校里，他们被年纪大的孩子打得很厉害，像九、十岁那样
who were like nine or ten okay
那就是斯巴达，第二个社会
that's Sparta the second society
was called the Aztecs Aztecs
被称为阿兹特克人 阿兹特克人
and
和
they also provided free compulsory
他们还提供免费义务教育
education to all its children really good right
教育对所有孩子都很重要，对吧？
and the third society is called Prussia
第三个社会叫做普鲁士
and actually Prussia is a system
实际上普鲁士是一个系统
that everyone uses today do you guys know any history
那是今天大家都在用的，你们知道历史吗？
okay what is common about all three societies Sparta Aztecs
好了，斯巴达、阿兹特克和普鲁士这三种社会有什么共同点？
and Prussia hmm
嗯，普鲁士呢？
what is common to all three three
三者共通之处是什么？
okay War War
好了，战争，战争
War War War War War War War War War War War War War War
战争，战争，战争，战争，战争，战争，战争，战争，战争，战争，战争，战争
War War War War War War War War War War War War War War War
战争，战争，战争，战争，战争，战争，战争，战争，战争，战争，战争，战争，战争，战争，战争
War War right?
战争，战争，对吗？
It's the Spartan warrior. Okay?
那是斯巴达战士。好吗？
The Aztecs were the greatest
阿兹特克人是中美洲最伟大的战争社会
war society in Central America before the arrival of the Europeans.
在欧洲人到来之前的时代
They defeated everyone.
他们击败了所有人
They were engaged in war.
他们也在战争中投入。
They also did a lot of human sacrifice as well.
他们也做了大量人祭。
Okay, we learn about the Aztecs later on.
好的，稍后我们再学习阿兹特克人。
Prussia, the Prussians,
普鲁士，普鲁士人，
the greatest military in Europe for centuries.
在欧洲数百年里是最强大的军队。
They were engaged in war making as well.
他们也从事战争制造。
Okay, do you understand this?
好的，你明白了吗？
Why we have schools is because schools
我们有学校的原因是因为学校
are really good at preparing people for war.
学校真的很擅长把人准备好去打仗。
Why? Excuse me?
为什么？请问一下？
What is, what is, why, why?
什么，什么，为什么，为什么？
Let me, Let me ask you this question. Why did they not have schools before?
让我，先问你一个问题。为什么他们以前没有学校？
Why is it that people were like, we don't want schools, why?
为什么人们会说我们不想要学校，为什么？
Again, the exporter, assets and
再说一次，出口商、资产和……
pressure were the few societies that had free public schooling.
压力是少数拥有免费公立学校的社会。
Why didn't other societies just copy them?
为什么其他社会没有直接复制它们？
Why? In order to be trained with mind.
为什么？为了用心灵训练？
Okay, let me ask you this question. Let's just say you're a mother or father.
好了，我来问你个问题。假设你是父母。
And you have a child, right?
你有个孩子，对吧？
What's the worst thing that could happen in your life?
你生命中最糟糕的事是什么？
No parents? No, no, your mother or your father.
没有父母？不不不，是你的母亲或父亲。
You have a child, right?
你有个孩子，对吧？
What's the worst thing that can happen to you in your life?
你生命中最糟糕的事是什么？
Your child is taken away from you, right?
你的孩子被带走了，对吧？
What does school do?
学校做什么？
School is designed to take your child away from you,
学校的设计是把孩子从你身边带走，
okay? Let me ask you this question.
好了，我来问你个问题。
If school is about learning, why don't parents and children go to school together?
如果学校是学习的事，为什么父母和孩子不一起去学校？
Yeah, why not?
是啊，为什么不呢？
Why? Because they have to work to survive.
因为他们得工作才能维持生计。
Because parents have to work to survive, right?
因为父母得工作才能维持生计，对吧？
There's actually a better reason why.
实际上还有更好的理由。
School is compromised in the social.
学校在社会层面已被打破。
They must have two people to do something.
他们必须有两个人来完成这件事。
Okay, it's about brainwashing, right?
好的，主要是脑洗，没错吧？
Because how do you brainwash someone?
那你怎么把人脑洗呢？
They're too old to talk to. Right?
他们太老了，没法再聊，吧？
If you're with your parent, are you gonna be brainwashed?
如果你和父母在一起，你会被洗脑吗？
No, because you feel loved.
不，因为你感到被爱。
You feel secure. Your parents are gonna protect you.
你会觉得安全。父母会保护你。
You're gonna ask your parent, hey, is this teacher, is he or she lying to me?
你会问父母，嘿，这位老师，他/她在跟我说谎吗？
And the parent's like, yeah, he's lying to you, okay?
父母会说，嗯，他在跟你说谎，好的？
It's only because you've been taken away from your parent
只是因为你被从父母身边带走，才会愿意被洗脑。
that you are now willing to be brainwashed.
为什么？因为离开父母后会发生什么？
Why? Because what happens if you leave your parents?
Why? Because what happensif you leave your parents?
How do you feel? How do you feel?
你感觉怎样？你感觉怎样？
Insecure. Insecure.
不安。不安。
Insecure. Yeah, exactly, right?
不安。对，正是如此，对吗？
Insecure. You're anxious.
不安。你焦虑。
You're afraid. You understand?
你害怕。你明白吗？
You've lost your parent. You're four, you're five, you're six years old.
你失去父母。你四岁、五岁、六岁。
You've lost your parent. You feel really insecure.
你失去父母，感觉很不安。
So who do you trust?
那么你信任谁？
Teacher. Your teacher. What if your teacher says, is now correct?
老师。你的老师。假如老师说，才是正确的？
One of our parents is also brainwashed.
我们的父母之一也被洗脑了。
Because they went to school before when they were school.
因为他们以前上学时就去过学校。
Yeah, okay, that's a great point, okay?
好，好的，这点很不错，明白吗？
Aren't our parents brainwashed as well?
我们的父母也被洗脑了吗？
That's correct. Your parents are brainwashed.
没错。你的父母被洗脑了。
But what I'm saying is, when a parent is with a child, the child feels secure.
我说的是，父母在孩子身边时，孩子会觉得安全。
And if you're secure, you're much more willing to disobey authority.
如果你感到安全，你就更愿意不服从命。
You're much willing to ask questions.
你更愿意提问问题。
You're much willing to think for yourself.
你更愿意自我思考。
Because you feel secure. Because your parent is there to protect you.
因为你感到安全。因为父母在身边保护你。
But if you take the parent away, you can't do that.
但如果把父母移走，你就做不到这件事。
You must now rely on the teacher, who can now brainwash you.
你现在必须靠老师，老师就能把你洗脑。
Okay? So are you brainwashing us?
好的？那你们在洗脑吗？
Am I brainwashing you? Okay.
我在洗脑你吗？好的。
It's a job too. Okay, all right.
这也是一份工作。好的，全部完成。
Okay, so the question is, am I brainwashing you?
好的，那问题是，我在洗脑你吗？
Okay, that's a good question.
好的，这是个不错的问题。
And it's a fair question. And again,
而且这是个合理的问题。
that's why I tell you this.
这就是我告诉你的原因。
Okay? You have the capacity to ask me questions.
好吧？你有能力向我提问。
You have the capacity to challenge me.
你有能力来挑战我。
You have the capacity to think for yourself.
你有能力自己思考。
Okay? So all I'm saying is, hear me out,
好吧？所以我说的只是，先听我说，
ask me questions, and then think for yourself whether or not I make sense.
问我问题，然后自己思考我说的是否有道理。
Because the difference between my class and other classes is like, I don't test you.
因为我的班级和其他班级的区别在于，我不做测验。
Right? I don't give you grades. It's a pass -fail class.
对吧？我不给你成绩。是及格-不及格的班级。
You can actually choose to say, you know what?
你实际上可以选择说，你知道吗？
This is nonsense. I don't want to listen anymore.
这没道理。我不想再听了。
I can't stop you.
我没法停住你。
Okay? But in school, guess what happens if you don't come to school?
好吧？但在学校，猜猜如果你不去上学会怎样？
Your parents get arrested. All right?
你的父母被逮捕。好吧？
Do you understand? That's the difference.
你明白了吗？这就是区别。
It's your choice whether or not to pay attention or not.
你是否注意到，是否不注意，都是你的选择。
All right. So now the question is, okay,
好的。现在问题是，嗯，
if schools are designed to bring you in,
如果学校是为了把你拉进去，
to brainwash you, what are they brainwashing you in?
洗脑，你们被洗脑成什么？
Well, they're designed to brainwash you to believe a concept
好吧，他们是为了洗脑你，让你相信一个概念
called the nation state.
叫做民族国家。
The nation state.
民族国家。
The schools are designed to brainwash you to think the nation state exists.
学校是为了洗脑你，让你认为民族国家存在。
It is a person, mother China.
它是一个人，母亲中国。
You must love this person.
你必须爱这个人。
You must be willing to sacrifice yourself for this person.
你必须愿意为这人牺牲自己。
You must be willing to take it yourself, to this person, because it is mother China.
你必须愿意为这人承担，因它是母亲中国。
And how do we brainwash you?
我们怎么洗脑你？
We teach you language, right?
我们教你语言，对吧？
We teach you history.
我们教你历史。
We teach you geography.
我们教你地理。
We teach you all this to make you believe
我们把这一切教给你，让你相信
that the nation state, mother China,
那民族国家，母亲中国，
the United States, France, they all exist.
美国、法国，它们都…
But guess what? For most of human history,
但你猜怎么了？在大部分人类历史里，
it was absurd to think the nation state existed.
它荒诞地认为民族国家存在。
Okay? Before,
好的？之前，
I'm Chinese. Before you say, I'm a Beijing -er.
我就是中国人。你说我来自北京。
Or I'm from Hai Dian.
或者我来自海淼。
Or I'm from Chaoyang, right?
或者我来自朝阳，对吧？
Because that makes more sense.
因为这样更有道理。
You're from a place where you know the people.
你来自一个你了解人们的地方。
But now, because of the nation state, you are forced to believe
但现在，因为民族国家，你被迫相信
that you are the same person as someone from Yunnan,
你和云南人是同一个人
Tibet, Guangxi.
你和藏人、广西人是同一个人
Even though, guess what guys, you have absolutely nothing in common.
即便如此，猜猜吧，伙计们，你们完全没有共同点。
But you're all Chinese. And that's what school is designed to do.
但你们都是中国人。正是学校的设计所做的事。
School is designed to implant in
学校的设计是为了植入
you a false memory of a nation state.
你是民族国家的虚假记忆。
Okay? That's what history is.
好的？这就是历史。
History is the false memory of a nation state.
历史是民族国家的虚假记忆。
And it happens. And
于是就发生了。然后
that's why you're all forced to go to school.
这就是你们被迫去上学的原因。
Okay? Maybe,
好的？也许，
like, we also want you to just,
像，我们也想让你只，
you know, think about degrees and work as a normal person,
你知道，想想学位和工作，像个普通人一样，
not to create a people business or live by yourself.
不必为人民事务而生。
Yeah. So, yeah. So,
是的。于是，嗯。于是，
the point of school is to serve the nation state.
学校的目的就是为民族国家服务。
Do you understand? Oh. Right?
你明白了吗？哦。对吗？
Does that make sense? If you believe in the nation state, if you believe in Mother China, then you must serve her.
这有道理吗？如果你相信民族国家，如果你相信母亲中国，那么你就必须为她服务。
You must obey her. You must fight for her.
你必须服从她。你必须为她而战。
You must die for her. Okay? So
你必须为她而死。好吗？
the idea of the nation state was created
民族国家的概念被提出
in order to make you obedient to authority.
以使你服从权威
And it works very effectively. Yeah?
它运作得非常有效。对吗？
I'm just wondering if this only works out in Chinese countries,
我只是想知道这是否只在中国等国家有效？
like, all the countries.
像，所有国家。
All countries. All countries are nation states.
所有国家。所有国家都是民族国家。
Okay? So, I mean, like, I'm not saying China is different from other places.
好的？我想说的是，我不是说中国和其他地方不一样。
China is exactly the same as other places.
中国和其他地方完全一样。
Okay? What you will learn in this class is how do we get to this place?
好的？这门课你将学到的是我们如何到达这个地方？
Because, again, the three things that we learn, okay?
因为，刚才说的三件事，明白吗？
Money. The individual.
钱。个人。
The individual. The nation state.
个人。民族国家。
These are all ideas and
这些都是概念而已
concepts beyond the human experience.
超越人类经验的概念。
If you try to work this out from first principles,
如果你从第一原理去推算
if you try to figure this out by yourself, you couldn't do it.
如果你自己想推算出来，做不到的
You have to be brainwashed into believing these three things.
你必须被洗脑成相信这三件事。
If someone from the past, maybe a thousand years ago, were to come today,
如果过去的某人，或许多年前的某人，今天来到这里，
and you would explain the concept of money, individual,
并且你会解释金钱的概念，个人，
and nation state, the person would be like, wait a minute here.
以及民族国家，那个人会说，等一下。
This means that you're all slaves.
这意味着你们全都成了奴隶。
Okay? So, now the question
好的？那么，现在的问题是：
then is, where do we get these three concepts from?
然后是，哪儿得到这三概念？
Where do we get these three concepts from?
哪儿得到这三概念？
Where do we get these three concepts from? Where do we get these three concepts from?
哪儿得到这三概念？哪儿得到这三概念？
Where do we get these three concepts from? Where do we get these three concepts from? Where do we get these three concepts from?
哪儿得到这三概念？哪儿得到这三概念？哪儿得到这三概念？
Where do we get these three concepts from?
哪儿得到这三概念？
called monotheism.
被称为单神论。
The one true God.
唯一的真神。
This idea, monotheism,
这个概念，单神论。
forever changed the course of human history.
永远改变了人类历史的进程。
They gave us these concepts of money, individual,
它们给我们带来了钱、个体和民族国家的概念。
and nation -state.
Monotheism is such a powerful idea that
单神论是如此强大的概念，
it turned nothing into everything.
它把一无所成为一切。
Okay, that's what you will learn in this class.
好的，这就是你在这门课里学到的内容。
We will learn about monotheism, we will discover how it created money,
我们将学习单神论，探究它如何创造了金钱、个体和民族国家，并且它基本上塑造了我们今天所处的世界。
individual, and the nation -state, and it basically created the world that we live in today.
Okay? All right.
好的？好了。
Okay. Any questions?
好的。还有问题吗？
Is Christianity monotheistic?
基督教是单神论的吗？
Excuse me? Christianity is like monotheistic.
请问一下？基督教是单神论的吗？
Okay, yeah. So there are three great monotheistic religions, right?
好的，嗯。 那么有三大单神论宗教，对吧？
Judaism, Christianity, and Islam.
犹太教、基督教和伊斯兰教。
What I will show you later on is, it's basically the same religion.
我稍后要给你展示的，基本上就是同一种宗教。
Yeah. Yeah. All right.
嗯。嗯。好的。
Okay, so I don't want to give you too much information, okay?
好的，我不想给你太多信息，好吗？
Because it's a lot to process.
因为这很大
But I want you guys to remember the concepts.
但我想让你们记住这些概念。
Money, individual, and nation -state are all powerful concepts
金钱、个人和民族国家都是强大的概念。
that are embedded into everyday life.
它们已嵌入日常生活中。
You cannot escape it. Okay, you've been brainwashed into thinking
你无法逃脱。好了，你已经被洗脑成这样想。
that they all exist, when in fact, they actually don't exist.
它们都存在，实际上却并不存在。
And that's how power works.
这就是权力的运作方式。
What power is, okay, what power truly is,
什么是权力，好吗，真正的权力是什么，
is what we'll call.
这就是我们要说的
.. alchemy.
炼金术。
Alchemy, throughout human history,
炼金术，贯穿人类历史。
was the pursuit of turning lead into gold.
铅变成金的追求。
Okay? Lead into gold.
铅变成金。
Okay?
好吗？
Nothing into everything.
无到有。
That's what alchemy was.
这就是炼金术。
And..
和…
. Maybe in science class, you're taught that alchemy is just fake science.
也许在科学课上，你们会被教到炼金术只是伪科学。
It's a pseudo -science. And it did not work.
它是一门伪科学，且确实没用。
What you will learn in this class is, we achieve alchemy.
你将在这门课里学到的，就是我们实现炼金术。
Okay? We turn nothing into everything.
好吗？我们把无物变成有物。
We turn lead into gold.
我们把铅变成金。
Or, that's what power is.
或者，这就是力量的本质。
Power is the capacity to turn nothing into everything.
力量是把无物变成有物的能力。
Power is the capacity to make you believe that money is valuable.
力量是让你相信金钱有价值的能力。
That the individual can lead to happiness.
那个人可以走向幸福。
That the nation -state exists.
那民族国家存在。
That's what power is.
这就是力量的本质。
Okay? And as a result,
好的？于是，
today we live extremely miserable lives.
今天我们过着极其悲惨的生活。
Okay? So,
好的？
you've been taught to think that, oh, life just gets better and better.
你已经被教会想，哦，生活会越来越好。
What you will learn in this class is, actually,
你在这门课里学到的，实际上是，
nope.
不。
Okay? And
好的吗？而且
what's really important is, you will also learn in this class
真正重要的是，你在这门课里还会学到
that this was an accident.
这是一场意外的事。
Okay? This is an accident.
好的？这是一场意外的事。
It's an accident of the human imagination.
这是一场人类想象的意外。
It's because we didn't know what we were doing that we created this system.
因为我们不知道自己在做什么，所以才创造了这个系统。
So, what you will also learn is that, if you're able to control the human imagination,
所以，你还会学到的是，如果你能掌控人类想象，
you can use it to create a new system
你可以用它来创造一个新的系统
that allows for, you know,
让它能够实现，你知道的
eudaimonia, or the flourishing of the human intellect.
eudaimonia，即人类智力的繁荣。
Okay? Alright.
好吧？好的。
Any questions? Okay.
还有问题吗？好的。
So, that's it for today.
好了，今天就到此为止。
Okay? I'll see you guys next class. Bye.
好的？下节课见。拜拜。